World Federation of Trade Unions Reports and Minutes on Microfilm 5396 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
World Federation of Trade Unions Reports and Minutes on Microfilm
1945-1949
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
World Federation of Trade Unions
5396 mf
0.22 cubic feet
2 microfilm reels
Microfilm, minutes, proceedings.
Consists of selected materials from 1945 through 1949 microfilmed from the more extensive WFTU collection: 5595 World Federation of Trade Unions, 1945-1973.
3833904
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The foundation of the World Federation of Trade Unions was laid at the World Labor Conference which met in London in February 1945. During the war period a spirit of cooperation had developed among world trade unions which could not find expression in the International Federation of trade Unions since the IFTU would not admit either the CIO or the Russians. The World Labor Conference proposed a reorganization of the IFTU to included these two groups, but the IFTU rejected it.
The Conference ended with the setting up of a Committee of Forty and a temporary Secretariat in Paris. A second conference was held in Paris in September and October of 1945 which set up a permanent body representing all affiliated national union centers, and created an Executive Committee, a small Executive Bureau and a General Secretary.
Trouble arose immediately when the WFTU then attempted to bring the International Trade Secretariats into its orbit, which was opposed by the AFL. The collection consists of minutes of meetings and documents issued during the period 1945-1949 when the Communist unions were attempting to take over control of the WFTU. This eventually resulted in the formation of the ICFTU.
Scope and Contents
Records consist of the microfilmed minutes, proceedings and reports of WFTU Executive Bureaus and Executive Committees, produced and presented at WFTU conferences held in Paris (1945, 1947, 1949); Moscow (1946); Prague (1947); Rome (1948); San Francisco and Washington (1973).
Governance records (1945-1973) include minutes, resolutions and proceedings of the WFTU Executive Bureau, General Councils, and committees (1945-1973) and of joint meetings of the WFTU and International Trade Secretariats (1948); also financial statements of the WFTU (1945-1949).
Reports and publications (1946-1949) consist mainly of unpublished reports and some pamphlets produced and presented at the annual sessions of the Executive Bureau and General Councils of the WFTU; also reports pertaining to special policies and activities of the WFTU. Materials pertaining to the WFTU's internal organization discuss or document the creation of WFTU international trade departments and negotiations between WFTU and International Trade Secretariats (1948). Also include documents regarding relations between the WFTU and the United Nations, International Labour Organization, Congress of Industrial Organizations, American Federation of Labor, and Allied Commission (Berlin); and various conferences, including the Pan Asiatic Trade Union Conference, and the World Trade Union Congress (1948-1949).
Also, WFTU policy statements regarding union activity and socioeconomic conditions in Occupied Germany; Mexico and Latin America (1948); activities in Japan, and Portugal (1948).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5256: Adolph Germer Papers 5595: World Federation of Trade Unions Records
Denazification; Economic assistance, American; Emigration and immigration; Employee rights; Equal pay for equal work; Foreign trade and employment; International economic relations; International labor activities; Labor unions -- Egypt; Labor unions -- Japan; Labor unions -- Austria; Labor unions -- Burma; Labor unions -- Europe; Labor unions -- Germany (East); Labor unions -- Germany (West); Labor unions -- Greece; Labor unions -- Iran; Labor unions -- Israel; Labor unions -- Italy -- Trieste; Labor unions -- Italy; Labor unions -- Palestine; Labor unions -- Political activity; Labor unions -- Portugal; Labor unions -- South Africa; Labor unions -- Southeast Asia; Labor unions -- Spain; Labor unions -- Tunisia; Labor unions -- Vietnam; Monopolies; Nuclear warfare -- Social aspects; Race discrimination; Reconstruction (1939-1951) -- Europe; Social security; Women -- Employment; World politics; Youth -- Employment; Anti-unionism.; Coal mining -- Europe; Collective bargaining -- Professions; Working class -- Economic conditions; Steel industry and trade -- Europe; Agricultural laborers -- Labor unions -- International cooperation; Coal-miners -- Labor unions -- International cooperation; Foresters -- Labor unions -- International cooperation; Metal-workers -- Labor unions -- International cooperation; Miners -- Labor unions -- International cooperation; Textile workers -- Labor unions -- International cooperation; Workers' education.; Czechoslovakia -- Politics and government -- 1945-; Solidarity; Labor unions; Blum, Leon, 1872-1950; Carey, James B.; Germer, Adolph.; Green, William, 1870-1952.; Jouhaux, Leon, 1879-1954.; Krane, Jay; Kunetsov, V. V.; Morse, Wayne; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952.; Rostovsky, S.; Saillant, Louis; Santi, Fernando; Vivimari, R; Allied Commission; American Federation of Labor; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); International Labour Organisation; United Nations; World Federation of Trade Unions
3833904
- Reports an Minutes of the Sessions of the Executive Bureau and Executive Committee of the World Federation of Trade Unions. (Reel 1)
  - Proces-Verbal des 2me et 3me Session due Comite Administratif in Washington, DC and San Francisco, 1945; 1 (Reel 1)
    Scope and Contents
    82 pp. April 17 - May 4, 1945. In French
  - Session of the Executive Bureau held in Washington, DC, 1946; 2 (Reel 1)
    80 pp plus 10 pp. September 1946. Held in the offices of the CIO.
  - Session of the Executive Committee held in Prague, 1947; 3 (Reel 1)
    43 pp plus 5 pp. June 1947.
  - Session of the Executive Bureau held in Paris, 1947; 4 (Reel 1)
    116 pp plus 3 pp. November 18-24, 1947. Held at the headquarters of the WFTU.
  - Session of the Executive Bureau held in Rome, 1948; 5 (Reel 1)
    61 pp. April 30 - May 2, 1948.
  - Session of the Executive Bureau held in Rome, 1948; 6 (Reel 1)
    63 pp. April 30 - May 2, 1948.
  - Session of the Executive Committee held in Rome, 1948; 7 (Reel 1)
    136 pp plus 9 pp. May 5 -10, 1948.
  - Session of the Executive Bureau held in Paris, 1948; 8 (Reel 1)
    91 pp plus 14 pp. September 17-21, 1948.
  - Summary Record of the Meeting of the Executive Bureau in Paris, 1948; 9 (Reel 1)
    September 17-21, 1948. 72 pp.
    - Point 7 of the Draft Agenda, 1948; 10 (Reel 1)
      Report on the Trade Union Situation in Germany. 26 pp.
    - Item 14 of the Agenda, 1948; 10 (Reel 1)
      Rate of Affiliation Fees for certain National Centres. 6 pp.
    - Item 12 of the Draft Agenda, 1948; 10 (Reel 1)
      Communication from the General Secretary on the Trade Union Situation in Mexico and Latin America. 9 pp. In French
    - Item 3 of the Draft Agenda, 1948; 10 (Reel 1)
      Note on the Decisions and Correspondence concerning a Pan-Asiatic Trade Union Conference. 5 pp.
    - Item 3 of the Draft Agenda, 1948; 10 (Reel 1)
      Suggestions Submitted by the Executive Bureau concerning the Fact-Finding Commission and the Pan-Asiatic Trade Union Conference.4 pp
    - Item 4 of the Draft Agenda, 1948; 10 (Reel 1)
      Report on the Seventh Session of the Economic and Social Council. 31 pp.
    - Item 9 of the Draft Agenda, 1948; 10 (Reel 1)
      Information Concerning the work of members of the Commission of Enquiry to Japan. 5 pp.
    - Item 10 of the Draft Agenda, 1948; 10 (Reel 1)
      Draft Decision on Civic and Trade Union Liberties in India. 1 p.
    - Item 12 of the Draft Agenda, 1948; 10 (Reel 1)
      The Trade Union Situation in Portugal (Letter received by the World Federation of Trade Unions Secretariat). 6 pp.
  - Session of the Executive Bureau held in Paris, 1949; 11 (Reel 1)
    January 17-19, 1949.
    - C.I.O. notes by Jay Krane, 1949; 11 (Reel 1)
      34 pp. Loose papers omitted.
    - Statement by James B. Carey, 1949; 11 (Reel 1)
      6 pp. Loose papers omitted.
    - Statement by V. V. Kunetsov, 1949; 11 (Reel 1)
      15 pp. Loose papers omitted.
  - Session of the Executive Bureau in Paris, 1949; 12 (Reel 1)
    January 17-22, 1949. Loose papers omitted.
  - Session of the Executive Committee in Paris, 1949; 13 (Reel 1)
    January 28 - February 1, 1949. 167 pp plus 16 pp.
- The Administration and Finances of the World Federation of Trade Unions. (Reel 2)
  - Session of the Executive Bureau and Executive Committee in Moscow, 1946; 14 (Reel 2)
    June 17-25, 1946. Report on the Internal Organization of Departments of the World Federation of Trade Unions. 9 pp.
  - Session of the Executive Bureau held in Paris, 1946; 15 (Reel 2)
    December 10, 1946. Financial Statement and Balance from October 1, 1945 until September 30, 1946. Budget estimates for the year 1947.
  - Executive Committee and General Council in Prague, 1947; 16 (Reel 2)
    June, 1947. Financial Reports and Statements of Auditors.
  - October 1, 1945 through September 30, 1946, 1945-1946; 17 (Reel 2)
    5 pp.
  - October 1, 1946 through March 31, 1947, 1946-1947; 18 (Reel 2)
    3 pp.
  - Appendix, 19 (Reel 2)
  - Session of the Executive Bureau and Executive Committee in Rome, 1948; 20 (Reel 2)
    April 30 - May 10, 1948. Financial Statement and Balance Sheet from October 1, 1946 until September 30, 1948 and from October 1, 1947 until March 31, 1948. Draft Budget for 1948. 24 pp